Preliminary Inventory to the Murray Bookchin Papers TAM.160
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Murray Bookchin Papers
1950-2003
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Bookchin, Murray, 1921-2006
Biehl, Janet, 1953-
TAM.160
17.25 Linear Feet in 18 boxes
Murray Bookchin (January 14, 1921-July 30, 2006) was a libertarian socialist, political philosopher, speaker and writer. The founder of the social ecology movement within libertarian socialist and ecological thought, Bookchin is noted for his synthesis of the anarchist tradition with modern ecological awareness. He was the author of two dozen books on politics, philosophy, history, and urban affairs as well as ecology. The collection contains correspondence, unpublished writings (including essays and manuscripts of unpublished and published books), published writings, including translations of Bookchin's books, Green movement periodicals, reviews of Bookchin's books, printed ephemera and documents related to the Left Green Network, the Burlington, Vermont Greens, and other Green movements, including those in Europe, course outlines, and photographs.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Murray Bookchin and Janet Biehl in 2003; additional materials were sent by Janet Biehl in 2006 and 2014. The accession numbers associated with these gifts are 2003.002, 2003.005, and 2015.003.
Arrangement
The files are grouped into boxes by form or topic.
The files are grouped into 1 series:
Missing Title
I. Preliminary Inventory, 1950s-2003.
Historical/Biographical Note
Murray Bookchin (January 14, 1921- July 30, 2006) was a libertarian socialist, political philosopher, speaker and writer. The founder of the social ecology movement within libertarian socialist and ecological thought, Bookchin is noted for his synthesis of the anarchist tradition with modern ecological awareness. He was the author of two dozen books on politics, philosophy, history, and urban affairs as well as ecology. Bookchin was a radical anti-capitalist and vocal advocate of the decentralization of society, in particular in his writings on libertarian municipalism, a theory of face-to-face, grassroots democracy. He was a staunch critic of biocentric philosophies such as deep ecology and the biologically deterministic beliefs of sociobiology.
Bookchin was born in New York City to Russian Jewish immigrants and was imbued with Marxist ideology from his youth. He joined the Young Pioneers, the Communist youth organization, at the age of nine. He worked in factories and became an organizer for the Congress of Industrial Organizations. In the late 1930s he broke with the Communist movement and gravitated toward Trotskyism, working with a group publishing the periodical Contemporary Issues. Then gradually becoming disillusioned with the coercion he saw as inherent in conventional Marxism-Leninism, he became an Anarchist, helping to found the Libertarian League in New York in the 1950s. Bookchin began teaching in the late 1960s at the Free University, a counter-cultural Manhattan-based institution. This led to a tenured position at Ramapo State College in Mahwah, NJ. He also co-founded, in 1971, the Institute for Social Ecology at Goddard College in Vermont.
His book, Our Synthetic Environment, published under the pseudonym Lewis Herber six months before Rachel Carson's Silent Spring, described a broad range of environmental ills but received little attention. His essay "Ecology and Revolutionary Thought" introduced ecology as a concept for radical politics. His 1969 essay "Listen, Marxist!" warned Students for a Democratic Society against the threat of takeover by a Marxist group. The Ecology of Freedom, which he published in 1982, had a profound impact on the emerging ecology movement. From Urbanization to Cities(originally published as T he Rise of Urbanization and the Decline of Citizenship) traces the democratic traditions that influenced his political philosophy and defines the implementation of the libertarian municipalism concept. A much smaller work, The Politics of Social Ecology, written by his partner of twenty years, Janet Biehl, briefly summarizes these ideas. In 1999, Bookchin broke with anarchism and placed his ideas into the framework of communalism.
In addition to his political writings, Bookchin wrote extensively on his philosophical ideas, which he called "dialectical naturalism." The dialectical writings of Hegel, which articulate a developmental philosophy of change and growth, seemed to him to lend themselves to an organic, even ecological approach. His later philosophical writings emphasize humanism, rationality, and the ideals of the Enlightenment. Bookchin's last major published work was The Third Revolution, a four-volume history of the libertarian impulse in European and American revolutionary movements. He died of heart failure on July 30, 2006 at his home in Burlington, Vermont at the age of 85.
For additional information, see: http://dwardmac.pitzer.edu/anarchist_archives/bookchin/Bookchinarchive.html
Related Material at the Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Murray Bookchin Audiocassettes (OH #56)
Scope and Content Note
This unprocessed collection contains correspondence, notebooks, unpublished writings (including essays and manuscripts of unpublished and published books), published writings, including translations of Bookchin's books, Green movement periodicals, reviews of Bookchin's books, printed ephemera and documents related to the Left Green Network, the Green movement in Burlington, Vermont, and other Green movements, course outlines, and a small number of photographs.
NOTE: This collection is stored offsite and advance notice is required for use.
Sources
http://dwardmac.pitzer.edu/anarchist_archives/bookchin/Bookchinarchive.html
Anarchism.; Photographs.; Communalism.; Syllabi.; Reviews (document genre); Manuscripts for publication.; Printed ephemera.; Notebooks; Correspondence.; Social ecology.; Green movement.; Communism.; Bookchin, Murray, 1921-2006; Institute for Social Ecology (Plainfield, Vt.); Left Green Network (U.S.); Biehl, Janet, 1953-
- Series I: Preliminary Inventory, 1950s-2003
  - Murray Bookchin: Essay Manuscripts (1 of 3), 1950s-1994 (Box 1)
  - Murray Bookchin: Essay Manuscripts (2 of 3), 1950s-1994 (Box 2)
  - Murray Bookchin: Essay Manuscripts (3 of 3), 1950s-1994 (Box 3)
  - Burlington (Vermont) Greens and New England Greens Materials, undated (Box 4)
  - Left Green Network; Social Ecology (international), undated (Box 5)
  - Murray Bookchin: Book Manuscripts: Urbanization, Remaking Society (partial), Ecology of Freedom, John Ely Interview. Periodicals: Left Green Perspectives, Comment, Harbinger, undated (Box 6)
  - European Greens Materials, undated (Box 7)
  - Correspondence, Incoming, 1950s-1993 (Box 8)
  - Murray Bookchin: Books Translated into Other Languages (1 of 2), undated (Box 9)
  - Murray Bookchin: Books Translated into Other Languages (2 of 2), undated (Box 10)
  - Murray Bookchin: Books Not Previously Owned by Tamiment; Periodicals and Anthologies to which MB Contributed, undated (Box 11)
  - Murray Bookchin: Books Not Previously Owned by Tamiment; Periodicals and Anthologies to which MB Contributed., undated (Box 12)
  - Correspondence, Incoming (1994-2003); Reviews of Bookchin's Books; Articles about Bookchin; "Deep Ecology" fight materials, 1994-2003, undated (Box 13)
  - Politics of Cosmology (unpublished Bookchin ms.); Bookchin's Early Notebooks; Course Outlines, undated (Box 14)
  - Articles about Bookchin, remainder, 1993-2003 (see also Box 13); Several More Book Manuscripts., 1993-2003, undated (Box 15)
  - Unpublished Manuscripts; Handwritten Manuscripts, undated (Box 16)
  - Correspondence and Part of an Unpublished Manuscript., 1980s-1990s (Box 17)
    Scope and Content Note
    The manuscript is a later version of Part 1 of The Politics of Cosmology than that located in Box 14 in these Papers; it has extensive hand-written copy-editing and proofreading corrections on it.
  - FBI/FOIA Correspondence and Documents; Mailing List for Comment Newsletter; Photographs, 1920s-1980s (Box 18)
    Photographs include what appears to be a portrait of Bookchin as a child, a portrait of him in the military (perhaps circa 1940s), various shots of him circa the 1960s-1980s, and a portrait of two women, circa 1950s, probably family members.